This is David Heinemeier Hansson from
37signals and I'm here to show you MRSK.
MRSK is a new deployment tool that we've been
building to get us out of the cloud.
we are moving out of the cloud and onto our own bare metal servers,
and we didn't want to give up
all the advancements in containerization and so on,
and we also didn't want to run Kubernetes ourselves.
So this is the alternative.
We are slicing up our big machines with KVM,
then we're shoving Docker on them and we are
using MRSK to coordinate all our deploys.
We've already moved out our first application.
We're moving out another one today,
and shortly thereafter, we will be moving on to,
hey, the largest application that we have in the cloud,
it is coming out hopefully within the cycle of work.
Let's see exactly how long it takes.
There is definitely some reconfiguration to do.
But since these applications were all
built for Kubernetes in the cloud,
they don't need a bunch of work because we're
using the same underlying containerization strategy,
and that works very well with MRSK.
we can take all of that work and reposition it within MRSK,
and off we go.
In our case, that's going to end up saving us
about $7 million over the next five years.
I will have a link in the description below to that analysis,
to that cost breakdown so you can see exactly how it figures out.
but I believe that MRSK is
a much broader tool than just something that's going to save
medium to large SaaS companies like ours a bunch of money.
It is also something that's going to provide
portability and escape hatch for anyone who starts on the cloud,
because the cloud makes a lot of
sense when you're just starting out.
but if you don't use something like MRSK and if you somehow
get tied up into some proprietary functions on the cloud,
it can be a little tricky to get out again.
so MRSK is a great way to start,
MRSK is a great way to exit.
you can use MRSK for all those things,
and I will go through all of it in this video,
showing you how to deploy a application
to two different cloud providers.
we're going to use Hetzner and we're going to use a DigitalOcean,
but you can use any cloud provider that provides you
with IP addresses that run Linux on VMs underneath.
now, MRSK requires a bit of knowledge of both Linux and of Docker.
So if you're still totally new to both of those concepts,
I would continue to recommend that you use
a fully managed platform as a service provider,
such as Fly.io, such as Render or even good old Heroku.
Those platforms will allow you to get further, faster,
if you don't know anything about systems operations at all.
And then hopefully in time you'll learn
and then you can jump on the MRSK wagon
once your application takes off
and you need a bunch of servers
and you find it too expensive to continue in the cloud
and you wanna run in your own bare metal.
So with no further ado, let's jump into the demo.
Let's start with a basic Rails application
built off the latest development version of Rails.
that version includes a new default Dockerfile
that MRSK will use to create the containers
we're going to deploy to the servers.
Otherwise, it is quite standard.
We're just using Tailwind to make it look nice,
but this is the blog that I have done videos on
about a million times over the years.
The one new feature that's interesting is this /up.
That is a default health check that Rails will also include
from the next version that tells the MRSK setup
and container coordination when the application
is ready to accept requests.
So we're gonna use that a little bit later,
but let's carry on.
The first thing we're gonna do is we're gonna set up
our application on Hetzner.
We can do that simply by creating single VM
that we're gonna name ship-app-1,
and we're gonna create that and then grab that IP address
And then we're gonna set it up
into the MRSK configuration file.
the MRSK configuration file is called deploy.yaml.
We can copy off the basics here
and pop it into the conflict directory,
which is where it's gonna look for it by default.
You can change that if you want.
It contains these basic setups,
what the service is gonna be named,
where the image lives, how to find it, the registry.
I'm just using Docker Hub here.
And then we copy the IP address that we just set up
and put it into the list of servers.
Now, we're going to set up an environment file.
We're going to actually set up an environment template and use
this envify setup to render the templates.
This is how we can protect our secrets.
We can look them up in something like
1Password as I'm doing here with op.
After I've done that with my most registered password,
I'm obviously not going to show you.
Let's check things into Git and then we're going to deploy.
This is basically all we need to get off to the races.
We're going to deploy this quickly.
You're going to see I'm going to fast forward a bit.
we're using QEMU as emulation to build an x86 image on a Mac M2,
which means it takes about four minutes to build
that image for the first time before any of the caches are warm.
So I'm going to fast forward here,
but as you can see, things are running along.
We built the image,
we pushed the image to the registry,
we pulled the image down on the server.
Then first, we start Traefik.
That is the zero deployment load
balancer we're using to swap between versions.
Then we run that health check I just talked about.
You can see we actually have to try to run it a couple of times
because the container is not ready right away,
but it's built into MRSK to retry that
up to seven times with a dynamic back off.
Then we start the container with
the correct versions and we prune the old versions,
and now we're actually running on
Hestner on the single VM. Let's check that out.
So we grab that IP again and go to the browser and see,
it is up and the application is running on a fresh DB.
So we can create our first post here and just see
that everything is working as we expected it.
It does. we're running in the cloud.
This was literally all it took.
So let's change our application.
Just do a quick change to one of the templates.
We check that change in and then we deploy a new version.
Again, I'm going to fast forward a bit,
but as you see these things scroll by,
you'll see that a lot of the steps are already cached
and it goes much faster when you deploy the second time.
Now, on this step,
you might see an exception if you've been running Docker for a while.
It has an arrow on QEMU where it might run out of memory.
if that happens to you, just restart the Docker engine.
In a real production environment,
most of the times you will actually use
a remote Docker buildx setup.
You can designate a single server to be your build server that runs
x86 when you build it x86 images and it goes much faster and you have no problems.
But we're going to blow through here again and see that everything is basically happening as it was
before. We check things out, we again run the health check and see that the new version is good
before we switch over from the old version and now we are live with our change. Really good posts.
But where did the old post go? We just created a post, it was gone. Oh, that is of course because
because we were running SQLite.
That is the default for Rails.
So let's set up a real shared database here.
we're gonna set that up with another vm on Hetzner,
just calling it ship-db.
And then let's also set up another app server
so that we can see that there's actually two app servers
accessing the same database.
And as we're doing that, as you're using a database,
of course you should always use a firewall
so that you don't expose MySQL
or whatever database you're using directly to the internet.
So we're gonna set up that firewall here.
We're gonna actually set up two firewalls,
one firewall for the app servers that just allows SSH and port 80.
Then we're going to set up a second firewall for
the database that just allows the two app servers that we have,
a direct connection to MySQL on port 3306.
So once you have that set up, you have
some basic security in place.
So it's that everyone on the Internet
can't just connect to your database.
That is a really good habit to do.
You may still want to do additional things on top of that.
You can use an SSH bastion server.
MRSK allows you to do all of that stuff.
But now we have our firewalls,
and we are setting those up obviously with
the correct IPs for the App servers is that we
can actually access them from the App servers.
But let's also set up a load balancer.
Now we have two App servers,
we want to access those on a single IP address,
we can set that up and that load balancer can be
configured to use the same health check
as we're using when we're deploying.
It's just going to be on /op,
we're going to be looking for a 200 OK,
and we're going to name that the Ship-LB-App.
So now we also have the App Server running.
Now we need to change the configuration of our application,
such that we use MySQL instead of SQLite,
that requires us to do the change to bundle,
to add the MySQL gem,
and then change the configuration.
We're going to pop in the actual host here.
In the new configuration,
as you can see it in the deploy YAML,
it looks very much if you've used Docker compose,
something else like that.
that MRSK has a couple of extra neat little features
for setting things up and copying files over
in files and directories.
You can read all about that
on the MRSK configuration walkthrough.
But for our purposes here, it's just a MySQL 8 image.
We're running on this host that we just set up for it.
And through the env clear dbhost,
we're gonna tell the app servers
where that db server is running.
So that's the basic configuration to get things set up.
Oh yes, let me show you the file.
We're gonna set up the database with.
we're going to initialize it as
the MySQL image is booted into a container for the first time.
It has this neat little initialization feature
where you can create the database you use.
Then Rails, again with the next version,
has a Docker entry point that will set up the database for you,
if it doesn't exist already,
and if it does exist,
it's going to run the migrations that are pending.
So that is what we need for the image.
Now we need to again configure Rails such that
the database YAML file knows about the new server.
you see we're referencing an environment variable here,
db_host, and we're just using the same root password.
You can of course set up a dedicated user if that's what you
desire but we're just going to follow the basic setup here.
We're going to add that MySQL root password to our nth template.
You see I just came up with a funny little password here and we're going to run
MRSK nvify one more time such that template gets rendered out into .env,
such that the App servers actually has
the MySQL password available when they're going to run.
Let's check all that into Git and then we're ready to
deploy another version of this whole setup.
We're actually going to use setup.
Setup is a special version that also sets up these accessories,
as we call them, the database on the side.
You only need to do that once as you configure them.
So normally, we just run deploy,
but when you're setting up a new accessory,
you're going to want to run MRSK for the first time.
Now, we're actually all set up here to see
the app servers hitting our application directly,
and it's going to hit the application,
and it's going to hit it with
the MySQL database on the back-end.
We can see that it's actually being properly
consistent by changing the index file we were changing before,
and once more deploying a new version of the app,
says that we can see the change without
losing the data we had put into our database.
So let's reload. Super duper good posts.
Awesome. Here's some other commands that you can run.
You can run "merc details" which gives you
an entire outlay of all the containers that we've started,
their names, their ports,
how long they've been up.
That is really helpful if you want to look at rollback,
which we're going to do in a second.
Here you can see we also have access to the app logs.
They just show all the health checks that have been going on.
Not terribly interesting, but here it is for both servers.
You can see it pulls for both of them and
displays them in the same setup.
We can do the same thing for the accessory.
It just gives us the boot log for
the MySQL 8 database that we've started.
Then the same thing for Traefik.
See, it is just looking at the back-end here.
Now, let's go back to those containers.
let's run a MRSK app containers instead of details.
Now we see all the containers that have been
started and then stopped again,
because that gives us the running
log of all the versions that we've been deploying.
We can take one of those older versions and we can
copy the version number,
those version numbers are just Git hashes,
but these are the ones that Merce
uses to determine whether you're on the right version or not.
Then we can do a rollback.
When we're doing a rollback,
we take a container that already lives on the server,
and then we say,
"Hey, stop the one you're currently running,
start that old one," and it goes really fast.
It doesn't have to build anything.
It doesn't even have to turn the image into a container.
Container already exists, and you can see here,
we've rolled back to just really good posts.
Now let's set up this IP address we have pointed to
the load balancer with a real domain name,
and we're going to do that on cloudflare.
I have a root domain here,
exitsoftware.io, and we can set that
up with a new DNS record for a subdomain.
We're going to use ship, and we're going to point it to
the IP address for the load balancer we had set up on
heads node that hits both of these apps at the same time.
So with that setup,
jump back here and hit it right on the domain, and boom.
You see exactly the same.
You see the beautiful little lock.
that means that there's SSL termination
happening at cloudflare,
and now your application is protected like that.
If we reload here,
you can see that all the assets are
being served over HTTP3 in fact,
and if we dive into these assets,
you can also see that they're being compressed.
we get all these things through cloudflare,
which means that the application that we're running,
does not have to worry about it.
You do not have to set up Let's Encrypt,
or Compression, or anything else.
You don't even have to have Nginx in front of it.
We're serving these assets straight off the Puma server,
but we're only doing it once per unique assets,
and then cloudflare or any other cdn you wish to use,
will take over and just use that.
So let's now try to create
a new post now that we're running in production.
Everything is great. Whoa, no, everything is not great.
What is going on?
4.2.2 here, we're getting an error message.
Let's scroll down, grab the request ID from the logs,
and look up what's going on.
The app logs feature has a -g,
which is a grep feature and you can give it
that request ID and we can look up just that request.
We can see when we look up that request,
we get the entire backtrace of the problem here,
and if we scroll up, we can see that there's an origin mismatch.
That is happening because we're doing
SSL termination with cloudfront,
but then we're forwarding the request to a network load balancer on
Hetzner that doesn't know anything about whether this is ssl or not.
It doesn't forward the correct headers.
We actually have to do that ourselves.
Luckily, the next version of Rails also have all that stuff built in.
we can talk along this config.assumeSSL feature
that basically just assumes that you're set up in the way that we've been doing it here,
that you have an SSL terminating load balancer cdn in front of your app,
and that your app should just assume that
everything is running over HTTPS.
when you do it, you can also turn on forceSSL,
which will set everything up with
the strict transport security and
all the other goodies that you would want when SSL is on.
Let's check that in and then redeploy
everything to the servers once more.
Redeploy is a variation
of deploy that just skips a couple of things.
It doesn't actually check whether
Docker is installed on the host already,
it doesn't prune, doesn't do a few of
those setup steps that you would
normally do when you deploy for the first time.
This is very convenient when you just want
things to go a little faster.
Faster it is, you can see here we
finished the entire deploy in 43 seconds.
Even though we're going through
QEMU emulation here to create our containers,
so much of that container was just
kept in cache and it goes really fast.
Again, it goes even faster if you're using an x86 build host.
We're now deploying things in 20 seconds or less.
Sometimes, it's really neat when you are used to
a slow build CI process that might take several minutes.
All right, let's go back and actually create that post again,
and you can see this time it succeeded.
We have both of our posts running the latest,
really super duper good post version of the app.
Two apps running behind a loan balancer to a database.
We are running pretty sweet here for a quite realistic setup.
So let's do it all again.
This time on DigitalOcean,
we will set up the entire system that we just created with three VMs,
two for app, one for a DP.
We're going to set up again, including everything.
We're going to set it up with the firewalls,
we're going to set it up with the load balancer,
we're going to add everything up as you would in real life,
and you'll see just how incredibly quick it is to
port your system from one provider to another.
This is really important not just hopping back and forth
between cloud providers, but obviously hopping from a cloud provider to bare metal hardware
you own yourself once that equation makes sense to your business here.
so this is really the power of MRSK.
it gives you incredible portability, jumping back and forth between cloud providers, jumping
back and forth between bare metal setups that you might have yourself.
You're never going to be locked in.
this is all just running on top of docker that has been instrumented through MRSK
and you can run it on any set of IPs that are thrown,
the deploy.yaml's way.
So let's set up the new deploy.do.yaml.
This is the second deploy file,
and it's going to be a specialization of the first.
So we just need to boil it down to the things that need to
change and the things that need to
change are just the IP addresses.
Everything else we're going to reuse
the configuration form, Hetcher form.
We copy and paste in the app servers,
we copy and paste in the database server,
and then we're basically going to be ready to go
and to deploy this whole thing on DigitalOcean.
We use -d, that is short for destination.
That is what Merce calls these alternate configuration.
That destination could be staging,
it could be Beta,
it could be another cloud provider,
whatever you like to use.
So it's running through everything that we've
seen a couple of times before now,
and obviously I sped that up a little bit.
It takes a little longer when you deploy it for the first time,
we have to install the software,
but it doesn't take that long.
It takes just a couple of minutes.
Now, let's change over our ship.exit software.io to
run on DigitalOcean and then see if we're running there.
We are. We're running the same version of the app,
but obviously with a new database from scratch,
we can create our new setup here,
and now we're running on DigitalOcean.
Let me show another quick feature.
This is really neat. This is the audit feature.
It is quite nice to see what's been going on the server,
who's been doing what, who's been pushing
different versions to the application.
and you can see all that in here.
It keeps a log on each servers.
And there's even a bonus feature I'm not gonna show here,
but you can post these audit broadcasts
to a campfire and base camp or another chat tool
that you might be using and follow along as you would.
It's all built in.
In addition to that, we can individual commands,
executions on the servers.
Here we're running an execution on both of the servers
and we're just asking for the Rails version
on both of those things.
And you can see here we're running 7.1, the alpha version.
We can also start a console, and we're
going to start a console here on DigitalOcean.
It is basically going to boot up an interactive session
on the existing container that already runs the app.
If you don't use dash reuse, you will
start a new container, which can be helpful in some cases.
But here, we're just reusing the same thing.
And you will see we can interact with our domain model,
with our database.
We can update that domain model and the database
straight from here.
If we pop back in, boom, you can see from the console.
That is very helpful and makes it easy to operate your application in production.
So, if we cut out of that, we are basically done.
now we can run MRSK remove because we don't want to leave our application
running on these cloud hosts.
I'm going to take everything away.
There's a confirmation here when you remove the database because obviously your
data's going to be blown away in this instance.
We're going to also remove it from Digital Ocean.
And that is it.